Broadsides by Jose Guadalupe Posada 1884-1920
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Broadsides by Jose Guadalupe Posada, 1884-1920
MS 523
Posada, José Guadalupe 1852-1913
A Collection of 50 broadsides(news sheets)or “Hojas Volantes”; many with José Guadalupe Posada illustrations on political topics, crime, bullfighters, corridos and humorous subjects.
2 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://www.library.arizona.edu/speccoll
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Jose Guadalupe Posada was a Mexican political illustrator, printmaker and engraver. He was born February 2, 1852 in Aguascalientes, Mexico to a poor family of nine children. Posada was taught to read, write, and draw by his older brother Cirilo, a country school teacher.
He learned engraving and lithography in Trinidad Pedroso’s Workshop of Popular Graphics. In his late teens Posada began his career as a political cartoonist for El Jicote the local newspaper in Aguascalientes owned by Trinidad Pedroso. Jose G. Posada then moved to the city of Leon, Guanajuato, where he married Maria de Jesus Vela on September 20, 1875. In Leon, Posada and Pedroso ran a small printing and commercial illustration shop which concentrated on commercial and advertising work, illustration of books, and the printing of posters of historical and religious figures. In 1883 Jose G. Posada became a teacher of lithography at the local Preparatory School. In 1888 he moved to Mexico City after a disastrous flood devastated the city of Leon. In 1889 he began working as s a draughtsman at Antonio Vanegas Arroyo’s printing house. In a career that lasted over 40 years he created thousands and thousands of images. Posada is best known for his costumed skeleton characters or Calaveras which he used as a source for his political and social satire. His skeletons have become associated with the Mexican holiday Día de los Muertos, the "Day of the Dead".
Jose G. Posada was largely forgotten by the end of his life. He died penniless and out of favor with local officials on January 20, 1913 in Mexico City. He was buried in an unmarked grave.
Posada's illustrations were brought to a wider fan base in the 1920s by the French artist Jean Charlot who called him the “printmaker to the Mexican people.” His work has gone on to influence many modern day Latin American artists and cartoonist.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 1 box with 50 broadsides.
Scope and Content Note
Jose G. Posada worked with the publisher Vanegas Arroyo during the years 1889-1912. This collection is a selection of news sheets from that tumultuous but fascinating period of Mexican history. The gamut of topics covered are: Sensationalized crime accounts, bullfighters accused of rape, politics - including two rare broadsides relating to Fransisco I. Madero, the Mexican Revolution, exploits of particular military leaders, natural disasters, humorous, verse, religious miracles and the like.
Access Terms
Posada, Jose Guadalupe, 1852-1913.
Vanegas, Antonio.
Antonio Vanegas Arroyo (Firm), publisher.
Mexico--Politics and government.
Broadsides--Mexican.
Broadsides--Mexico.
Engraving, Mexican.
Mexico--Politics and government.
Mexico--History.
Container List
- A list of 50 broadsides, many with Posada illustrations and dates if printed on items: 1884-1920
  - Libertad Caucional Del Famoso Diestro Rodolfo Gaona., [1910]; 12 x 16 inches.; Uncut double sheet with two printing of the two sided broadsheet. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Story of a famous bullfighter accused of taking advantage of an inebriated young female fan (Miss Maria Luisa Noecker), the girl ended up committing suicide after some other perpetrator apparently raped her,
  - Marieta. Cancion Moderna. Tiempo De Polka., 1914; Uncut double sheet. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Despedida Del General Diaz., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    A "good bye - farewell" to General Diaz.
  - Asalto Al Tren De Cuenavac Por Los Excecrables Bandidos Zapatistas. 82 Muertos Y 17 Heridos!, undated; Uncut double signed sheet. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Describes violent train holdup in Cuernavaca by Zapatistas.
  - Espantosismo Crimen! Estrangulados la noche del 2 de Diciembre del presente. año en la casa num. 2 de la 1a. Calle de Matias Romero una cuadra antes de la penitenciarla., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Unsolved crime story about the strangulation of two poor children.
  - Las Derrotas de los Alzado Carrancistas., 1913 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Illustration of the "Una Mujer degollda" [decapitated] plus la muerte de chche campos a los separatistas Sonorenses. "Cheche campos fue uno de los rebeldes que mas simpatias inspiraba, por haberse lanzado de una manera desinteresada a la revuelta contra el gobierno del nefasto Francisco I. Madero
  - Verdaderos versos de Macario Romero., 1911; Uncut double sheet. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    "Valgame Dios, que veo! Cuanteo yaqui con guarache, y cuanto maldito apache con sus flechas de trofeo!" plus Corrido Del Zenzontle en verso. Corrido about Macario Romero who disobeyed General Plata and attended a dance where he was shot dead,
  - Ligitimos versos de lino zamora. Traidos del real de zacatecas., 1911; Uncut double sheet. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Adios, Adio! El Ultimo corrido de la despedida de chonforo vico., 1909; Uncut double sheet. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - El Sr. Presidente interino, la Candidatura del senor Don Franciso Leon de la Barra., undated; Photo portrait. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gaceta Callejera. Esta hoja se publicara cuando los acontecimientos de sensacion los requieren. Grande y sorprendente simulacro, Abril, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Instrucciones militares para los voluntarios que deseen tomar las armas, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jesus Bruno Martinez en las Barotolinas de Belen. Ultimas noticias de S. Juan De Ulua, las alhajas de treffiel, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Don Francisco I. Madero ante el peligro +Terrible mortandad, 75 muertos y cuarenta y dos heridos en la ciudad de Puebla, la noche del 12 Julio de 1911 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Impresiones del discurso del Senor Madero en Puebla + Noche Triste, del 12 de Julio de 1911 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - El Sargento Juan Diaz condenado a muerte. No hay esperanza de Salvacion para el reo., undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Details of the crimes commited by the cruel sargent during the Mexican Revolution.
  - La Mujer de cien maridos como alfileres prendidos, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - El Novio de mil mujeres les da dinero y placeres, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Versos legitimos del tipico Jarabe Morellano, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - La inundacion de Guanajuato y su causa verdadera, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - La Despedida de un Pachuqueno, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Valentina, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Memorias y recepcion en los profundisimos infiernos del bandido Nicolas Torres, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Los Huelguistas de Orizaba, corrido, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - La Continuacion, senores de los Pronosticos va; aprendanselos de memoria que ya se van a acabar., undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Horrorosa noticia, robo sacrilego y aseinato del Senor Cura en la Iglesia Parroquial del pubelo de Zahuaya, cometidos por un impio llamado Celso Flores, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - El Valiente Costeno, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - El General Don Pasqual Orozco sale para el norte a batir los traidores separatistas, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Aventuras de un catrin por amar un casada, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Gran alarma escandalosa que se vio alla por Chihuahua, al oir los tristes lamentos de un patito con teresa que no llena su barriga por causa de la pobreze, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - El Cadaver de Antonio Montes convertido en carbon en el deposito panteon Espanol de la captial de Mexico, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Ya la vieja de mi suegra no mas quiere reganar, de a tiro la corta verde no la deja Madurar, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Loa dicha por un petatero y un tortillera, en honor del Senor de las Maravillas, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Corrido Guanajuatense del horrible descarrilamiento de Silao, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Marrieta, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Corrido de Juan Dimio (del estado de Morelos), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Una Huerfana se lamenta y llora sobre la Tumba de las Madre, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Triste que tuvo en Mexico pues fue presto fusilado, Don Gustavo el Fatidico, El famoso Ojo Parado, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Corrido de petrita, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Legitimos versos de Lino Zamora traidos del real de Zacatecas, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - El Valiente de Guadalajara, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Horrible asesinato! Una ama de llaves que mata al Cura De S. Geronimo Distrito de Otumba, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Milagro patene! La imagen de Sagrado Corazon de Jesus, de aparece en una hostia consagrada, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Lamentos del gral D. Benardo Reyes in la prision militar de Santiago Tlaltelolco, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Proximo fin del mundo. La horrible catastrofe del Domingo 14 de Abril de 1907 en Chilpancingo, Chilapa, Tixtla y Acapulco en el estado de Guerrero. Destruccion del Colegio Salesiano en la capital de Mexico (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Reciente pleito de casados que si no rinen Estan Enojados, undated; Double sheet uncut. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - La nunca vista Nevada del dia 11 de Febrero del presente ano, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Loa dicha por una cocinera y un aguador, en honor de nuestra Senora del Rosario, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Vista y despedimiento al Senor de Ixtapalapa. Que se venera en dicho Pueblo, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Ay, que Chula Eres, pachita! Me da ganas de besarte no mas no quieras platitas porque puedo hasta patearte y te iras con tu nanita a echar pulgas a otra parte. Amigo, voy a contarte lo que me paso en Morelia, que ya me corrio silveria a echar pulgas a otra parte, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)